<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>rOpenSci Biweekly</title>
    <description>rOpenSci biweekly updates, including for software, what&#39;s happening in the community, events, and more.</description>
    <link>/biweekly/</link>
    <atom:link href="/biweekly/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2015 08:15:38 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2015 08:15:38 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.3.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Update 2015-01-19</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;rvertnet&lt;/code&gt; update is useable now - we’d love feedback on the new version of the package, which works with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/VertNet/webapp/wiki&quot;&gt;new Vertnet API&lt;/a&gt;. This will get included in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/spocc&quot;&gt;spocc&lt;/a&gt; as another data source. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;fulltext&lt;/a&gt; package, we focus on getting open access full text of scholarly content. However, just to explore where it goes, we’ve been adding feaures to help simplify extraction of parts of articles. We shared a few gists recently describing how to &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sckott/9e021eb1c6a949158d69&quot;&gt;pull out chunks of articles and view them&lt;/a&gt;, how to &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sckott/e628be5c412a3bb38ffc&quot;&gt;coerce article data into data.frame’s&lt;/a&gt;, and a use case for &lt;code&gt;fulltext&lt;/code&gt; asking &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sckott/31bf9c6772038a704f95&quot;&gt;how long the time is between article reception and acceptance in PLOS journals&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We added scroll search to our R client for Elasticsearch &lt;code&gt;elastic&lt;/code&gt; - and shared &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sckott/675cf255f49f37032683&quot;&gt;a gist&lt;/a&gt; demoing its use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community&quot;&gt;Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We did our first community call on Wednesday, the 14th of January. It was fun and we really appreciate Ciera Martinez for discussing &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rrhack?src=hash&quot;&gt;#rrhack&lt;/a&gt;. We’ll put up video and notes from the call very soon. The main home for information on community calls is at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/commcalls&quot;&gt;ropensci/commcalls&lt;/a&gt; - see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/commcalls/issues&quot;&gt;issues page&lt;/a&gt; for an issue for each call. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-the-news&quot;&gt;In the news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rOpenSci got a mention in as &lt;a href=&quot;http://beautifulopen.com/2015/01/07/ropensci/&quot;&gt;Beautiful site in Open Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ouzor&quot;&gt;Juuso Parkkinen&lt;/a&gt; did a &lt;a href=&quot;http://ouzor.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/interactive-visualizations.html&quot;&gt;review of interactive vizualizations in R&lt;/a&gt;, including the plotly R client from our suite. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/taxize/&quot;&gt;taxize&lt;/a&gt; got a citation in a new paper in Molecular Ecology &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/mec.13026/abstract&quot;&gt;Comparative genomics in the Asteraceae reveals little evidence for parallel evolutionary change in invasive taxa&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/biweekly/update-2015-01-19/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biweekly/update-2015-01-19/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Update 2015-01-05</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first version of &lt;code&gt;gistr&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;v0.1.0&lt;/code&gt;) is up on CRAN. &lt;code&gt;gistr&lt;/code&gt; is an R client for working with GitHub gists. You can get gists and their metadata, and create them. A blog post describing the package: &lt;a href=&quot;http://recology.info/2015/01/gistr-github-gists/&quot;&gt;http://recology.info/2015/01/gistr-github-gists/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;rvertnet&lt;/code&gt; is getting a reworking based on the new Vertnet APIs. Check out the &lt;code&gt;udpate&lt;/code&gt; branch in the repo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/rvertnet/tree/update&quot;&gt;https://github.com/ropensci/rvertnet/tree/update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ckanr&lt;/code&gt; got a pull request from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/imanuelcostigan&quot;&gt;Imanuel Costigan&lt;/a&gt;, allowing easier setting of the base url for the CKAN instance. See gist for use: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sckott/c86f3c2965cfc389ac3c&quot;&gt;https://gist.github.com/sckott/c86f3c2965cfc389ac3c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We shared a Gist on getting elevation data for lat/long locations in the &lt;code&gt;rgbif&lt;/code&gt; package via the Google Elevation API (&lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sckott/2d3ae5f0cecca3deb436&quot;&gt;https://gist.github.com/sckott/2d3ae5f0cecca3deb436&lt;/a&gt;), and there was a cool look by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Md_Harris&quot;&gt;Matt Harris&lt;/a&gt; at how accurate the Google Elevation API is compared to Digital Elevation Models: &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpubs.com/mharris/GoogleAPI&quot;&gt;http://rpubs.com/mharris/GoogleAPI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We shared another Gist on getting NOAA NCDC data via FTP &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sckott/440222f040a3444057ad&quot;&gt;https://gist.github.com/sckott/440222f040a3444057ad&lt;/a&gt; - attempting to cover the use case where the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/cdo-web/webservices/v2&quot;&gt;NOAA NCDC API&lt;/a&gt; rate limits are lower than your data needs. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community&quot;&gt;Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New R package in the rOpenSci suite, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/rdopa&quot;&gt;rdopa&lt;/a&gt;, an R client to &lt;a href=&quot;http://dopa-services.jrc.ec.europa.eu/rest/&quot;&gt;Joint Research Centre’s DOPA REST API&lt;/a&gt;. This is also gives us a new contributor! &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jlehtoma&quot;&gt;Joona Lehtomäki&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New contibutor to rOpenSci via &lt;code&gt;rvertnet&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Pika8tona&quot;&gt;Chris Ray&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our new &lt;a href=&quot;http://discuss.ropensci.org/&quot;&gt;rOpenSci discussion forum&lt;/a&gt; is growing fast. Do join us there if you want to discuss all things rOpenSci. There’s login options for email, Twitter, GitHub, and Mozilla Persona. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ropensci-in-the-news&quot;&gt;rOpenSci in the news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rOpenSci got a mention in the bioRxiv preprint &lt;em&gt;Connecting people and ideas from around the world: global innovation platforms for next-generation ecology and beyond&lt;/em&gt; by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://innge.net/&quot;&gt;INGEE&lt;/a&gt; folks. See the abstract at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2014/12/14/012666.abstract&quot;&gt;http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2014/12/14/012666.abstract&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We (and &lt;a href=&quot;http://ropengov.github.io/&quot;&gt;rOpenGov!&lt;/a&gt;) got a mention in a manuscript in draft at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/muuankarski/rlang&quot;&gt;muuankarski/rlang&lt;/a&gt; on GitHub. &lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/muuankarski/rlang/master/r_lang.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Other such domain specific projects are for example rOpenSci and emerging rOpenGov that provide tools for open science and open government data, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A mention in &lt;a href=&quot;https://peerj.com/preprints/235v1.pdf&quot;&gt;a PeerJ preprint&lt;/a&gt; titled &lt;em&gt;Close connections between open science and open-source software&lt;/em&gt;. The mention is &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recently, rOpenSci (http://ropensci.org/) is released as a new in-progress collaborative project aiming to effectively and synergistically connect various online databases through R computing platform. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/biweekly/update-2015-01-05/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biweekly/update-2015-01-05/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>rOpenci Biweekly Updates</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve found it useful to collate all the notable things that happened in the last week or two with software, community, and events within rOpenSci - and send that around within our leadership team. We thought this might be useful to users, developers, and others in our community. Thus, we’re starting a new series of emails to send to this mailing list. These &lt;strong&gt;rOpenSci Biweekly Updates&lt;/strong&gt; will list all notable software updates, activity in our community (new members, cool things members have done, etc.), events in our community, and rOpenSci mentions in the news. As we all dislike getting too many emails, we’re only sending an update biweekly, or twice per month, on Mondays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve already done a few:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2014-12-15 - &lt;a href=&quot;http://ropensci.github.io/biweekly/update-2014-12-15/&quot;&gt;http://ropensci.github.io/biweekly/update-2014-12-15/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2014-12-22 - &lt;a href=&quot;http://ropensci.github.io/biweekly/update-2014-12-22/&quot;&gt;http://ropensci.github.io/biweekly/update-2014-12-22/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next one will be this upcoming Monday, 2015-01-05.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us know if you have any feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/biweekly/ropensci-weekly-updates/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biweekly/ropensci-weekly-updates/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Update 2014-12-22</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taxize v0.5.2 pushed to CRAN. Last version on CRAN was v0.4. This version has a lot of updates since v0.4. See releases: https://github.com/ropensci/taxize/releases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rnoaa v0.3.3 pushed to CRAN. Last version on CRAN was v0.2. This version has a lot of updates. See releases: https://github.com/ropensci/rnoaa/releases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We updated our packages page again (http://ropensci.org/packages/ ) -this time making it easier to navigate by sorting packages within each section alphabetically, putting deep link headers for each section (e.g,. http://ropensci.org/packages/#literature) on the top of the page, and allowing deep linking to each package (e.g., http://ropensci.org/packages/#taxize ). Thanks to Matt Jones for the suggestions. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;maptools&lt;/code&gt; TaskView is now operational https://github.com/ropensci/maptools in the sense that we can now run &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;, and it should work, so we can start populating…I started adding some sections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community&quot;&gt;Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are starting to roll out our community discussion forum, its at http://discuss.ropensci.org/ - Supports email, twitter, github, and Mozilla Persona login. Not sure when it will be fully public yet….&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We announced a repo for community calls https://github.com/ropensci/commcalls - where we’ll announce new community calls, and people can discuss topics related to community calls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two blog posts last week: One announcing community calls http://ropensci.org/blog/2014/12/15/community-calls/ and another on curl in R http://ropensci.org/blog/2014/12/18/curl-options/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;events&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karthik was at the American Geophysical Union Conference in SF http://fallmeeting.agu.org/2014/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ropensci-in-the-news&quot;&gt;rOpenSci in the news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just found that Karthik and ropensci got a shoutout in the book R for Cloud Computing: An Approach for Data Scientists https://books.google.com/books?id=DTRpBQAAQBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA220&amp;amp;lpg=PA220&amp;amp;dq=ropensci.org&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=gXG-JDo1sP&amp;amp;sig=t_3mIXtYuemzQCQ5iba6_ph4JFU&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=E5WTVIefNcvnoASHjYKwAg&amp;amp;ved=0CE4Q6AEwCTge#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=ropensci.org&amp;amp;f=false&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shoutout from SimplyStats blog http://simplystatistics.org/2014/12/17/a-non-comprehensive-list-of-awesome-things-other-people-did-in-2014/  &amp;gt; “rOpenSci ran an awesome hackathon. The lineup of people they invited was great and I loved the commitment to a diverse group of junior R programmers. I really, really hope they run it again.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shoutout to rOpenSci from Hadley in an interview http://bulletin.imstat.org/2014/12/hadley-wickham-impact-the-world-by-being-useful/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/biweekly/update-2014-12-22/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biweekly/update-2014-12-22/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Update 2014-12-15</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patch version &lt;code&gt;v0.2.1&lt;/code&gt; of rcrossref sent to CRAN. Release notes: https://github.com/ropensci/rcrossref/releases/tag/v0.2.1 - We’re in the process of adding content negotiation to this package, to get full text, where available, across any Crossref member publisher that participates. This will be heavily used in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/fulltext&quot;&gt;fulltext package&lt;/a&gt; to search for full text content. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New version &lt;code&gt;v0.5&lt;/code&gt; of taxize out. Release notes:  https://github.com/ropensci/taxize/releases/tag/v0.5.0  - Note that this version is not on CRAN as of this date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;elife&lt;/code&gt; R package is temporarily deprecated as they’re dropping their API soon https://github.com/ropensci/elife - Let us know if you would use an eLife API so we can communicate that to eLife. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We use &lt;code&gt;httr&lt;/code&gt; a lot in our packages. A recent addition in &lt;code&gt;httr&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;v0.6&lt;/code&gt; includes a way to deal with a problem you may have stumbled upon when working with data from the web. When a series of requests to get data from the web is interrupted, you often get an error like &lt;code&gt;easy handled already used in multi handle&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;httr&lt;/code&gt; now has the functions &lt;code&gt;handle_find()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;handle_reset()&lt;/code&gt; to help in this scenario. Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://recology.info/2014/12/multi-handle/&quot;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt; to find out more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We updated our packages page on our website (http://ropensci.org/packages/ ) with many new packages in development, and updated notes about packages (e.g., a package deprecation). Check it out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community&quot;&gt;Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We just announced that we’ll be starting to do community calls, Check out the blog post: http://ropensci.org/blog/2014/12/15/community-calls/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have a few new community members/contributors: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;First, Matt Pennel, maintaining the &lt;code&gt;chromer&lt;/code&gt; package (https://github.com/ropensci/chromer) to interact with Chromosome Counts Database (CCDB) http://ccdb.tau.ac.il.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Second, Abaghan Ghahraman, brings to the rOpenSci suite the R package rGEM (https://github.com/ropensci/rGEM) to connect to the Global Entrepreneurship Monitor (GEM) http://www.gemconsortium.org/&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Third, Kyle Hamilton joins rOpenSci, with two packages in development. RCryptsy (https://github.com/ropensci/RCryptsy) is a package to interact with the Public API for the Crypto-Currency exchange Cryptsy (https://www.cryptsy.com/). RStars (https://github.com/ropensci/RStars) is a package to access to the Digital Universe Data set (http://star-api.herokuapp.com/ )&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;events&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carl Boettiger, of the rOpenSci leadership team, was at NESCENT for &lt;em&gt;Reproducible Science Hackathon: Curriculum &amp;amp; Workflow Development&lt;/em&gt; (see http://www.nescent.org/cal/calendar_detail.php?id=1125). &lt;a href=&quot;http://cierareports.org/&quot;&gt;Ciera Martinez&lt;/a&gt; will be joining us at our first rOpenSci community call to discuss highlights of this event. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karthik Ram and Scott Chamberlain attended a &lt;a href=&quot;http://articlemetrics.github.io/workshop_2014/&quot;&gt;PLOS altmetrics conference&lt;/a&gt; in San Francisco. We maintain R clients for &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/raltmetric&quot;&gt;Altmetric.com &lt;/a&gt; and for the PLOS altmetrics application, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ropensci/alm&quot;&gt;Lagotto&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/biweekly/update-2014-12-15/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biweekly/update-2014-12-15/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
